1939, a few months before the start of World War II,
Nazi Germany. After approximately 304,000 Jews emigrated, only about 214,000
of them remain in the country. Six years of legislation pushed by the Nazis have marginalized
and deprived the rights of Jewish citizenship in Germany and expelled Jews from the
professions and commercial life. After the outbreak of the Second World War,
beginning on September 1, 1939, Nazi anti-Jewish policy becomes even more
radical and varies from country to country, including direct and brutal occupation and dependence
of collaborationist regimes. Children are especially vulnerable to Nazi persecution.
While some are persecuted for alleged racial reasons,
Others are disabled for biological reasons, such as patients with physical or mental disabilities,
or because of their alleged resistance or political activities. At the end of World War II,
No less than 1.5 million Jewish children will be murdered or die at the hands of Nazi officials
or their collaborators. Among them are 20 children from different countries in occupied Europe.
by Germany who will be killed on the night of April 20, 1945 because, after being used
as human subjects in medical experiments at the Neuengamme concentration camp,
Their Nazi torturers want to cover up their barbaric crimes by destroying all
the tests. These children will be injected with morphine and then
will hang mercilessly from hooks placed on the wall. However, this atrocity
will not go unpunished and the perpetrators will pay for this crime with their lives.
The Nazis defended the murder of children belonging to groups
“undesirable” or “dangerous”, whether as part of the “racial struggle” or as a measure of
preventive security. Thus, the Germans and their collaborators killed children for
These are ideological reasons and in retaliation for real or perceived partisan attacks.
As children were generally too young to be used in work
forced, became the first victims taken to graves
common to be shot. However, some did not go through this. Instead,
German authorities often selected the elderly,
sick and disabled people for the first deportations to the extermination centers.
Upon their arrival, the authorities of the concentration camps of Auschwitz-Birkenau and others
Extermination centers sent the vast majority of Jewish children directly
to the gas chambers. The German authorities also imprisoned numerous
children in concentration and transit camps. SS doctors and the
Medical researchers used numerous children, including twins,
in concentration camps and extermination centers such as Auschwitz for medical experiments that
often ended with the death of the children. Another concentration camp where doctors
Nazis carried out experiments on human beings was the Neuengamme concentration camp.
In the spring of 1944, Enno Lolling, the chief physician of all the concentration camps,
He ordered that one of the Neuengamme barracks be reserved for medical experiments.
secrets of Dr. Kurt Heissmeyer. Heissmeyer wanted to test how the body reacted
to injections of tuberculosis bacilli and to evaluate an antidote he had developed.
His experiments on about 30 Polish and Russian prisoners proved largely unsuccessful,
since most of them died. In the fall of 1944, Heissmeyer requested the transfer of children
Jews to serve as "guinea pigs" for their reckless theories.
At the end of November 1944, twenty Jewish children between the ages of 5 and 12 were taken to
Neuengamme from Auschwitz. Ten boys and ten girls from the Auschwitz concentration camp.
Auschwitz were selected by the doctor Josef Mengele, who asked the children:
"Who wants to go see their mother?" Most of them were from Poland,
while others came from France, the Netherlands, Italy and Slovakia.
The children were accompanied to Neuengamme by four prisoners. Three of them—two nurses
Polish women and a Hungarian pharmacist who also worked as a nurse – were murdered
her arrival at Neuengamme by the camp executioner Wilhelm Dreimann. The fourth woman,
The Polish-born Jew named Paulina Trocki was a doctor. She survived the war and later
He testified in Jerusalem about what he had witnessed. Trocki said the following:
"The transport was accompanied by an SS guard. There were 20 children, a doctor and three
nurses. The transport was in a separate car that was attached to a regular train. Presented
This way it looked like a normal wagon. We had to take off our Stars of David so as not to
to attract attention. To prevent people from approaching us, they said it was a transport
of people suffering from typhoid fever... The food was excellent; on that trip we were given
chocolate and milk. After a two-day journey, we arrived in Neuengamme at ten o'clock at night."
The children were housed in the same barracks where the
adult prisoners. After initial examinations, the children were infected with
live tuberculosis bacilli. Their skin was cut and the wounds were rubbed with sputum
which contained the bacteria. After a while, under Heissmeyer's supervision,
The swollen lymph nodes under their heads were surgically removed.
arms for examination. Each child underwent this painful procedure twice and also
They were photographed raising their arms to show the surgical incision. The terrible
The experience of these weakened, lonely, feverish children lasted for months. After the war,
When Dr. Heissmeyer was asked why he did not use animals as guinea pigs,
The doctor replied: “For me there was no basic difference between human beings
and the guinea pigs.” He then corrected himself, saying, “The Jews and the guinea pigs.”
By early spring of 1945, it was clear that Germany had lost the war and the Nazis,
In their eagerness to cover up their barbaric crimes, they began to destroy evidence. As part of
In this effort, the victims of Heissmeyer's experiments also had to disappear. Max
Pauly, the commandant of the Neuengamme concentration camp, received the order from the administrator
head of the Nazi concentration camps, SS-Obergruppenführer Oswald Pohl,
which stated that Heissmeyer's department was to be "disbanded" and that all children and
caretakers had to be killed so that no witnesses of this crime would survive.
Pauly passed the order on to the doctor Alfred Trzebinski,
who was responsible for the children's ongoing medical treatment.
The murder took place on the night of April 20, 1945 in the old building
Bullenhuser Damm school, which served as a subcamp of Neuengamme.
Around midnight, a small mail truck pulled up in front of the building. First,
They took six Russian prisoners out of the truck and took them to the back of the school,
where they were directed to the basement. Then, a group of 20 Jewish children followed in their footsteps. In the basement,
All the children were crammed into one room with Trzebinski. While the children,
who didn't know what was waiting for them, chatted quietly among themselves,
The Russians were silently murdered in the adjoining rooms. One by one, the
Russians were hanged with ropes draped over heating pipes. The executions
were carried out by SS men Ewald Jauch and Johann Frahm. After a while,
Frahm entered the room where the children were and ordered them to undress.
The terrified children looked questioningly at Trzebinski, who cynically assured them
who were to be vaccinated against typhus. During the post-war trial,
Trzebinski recalled how he took Frahm aside and asked him in a low voice, so that the children wouldn't
heard: "What will happen to them now?" Frahm replied that he had to hang them. Trzebinski
He then proceeded to inject the children with large doses of morphine. He and Frahm placed them
on the floor under blankets. Most of them, tired and sedated, fell asleep quickly,
while a few remained awake, talking quietly among themselves.
At least the first two children were hanged by Wilhelm Dreimann. Alfred Trzebinski recalled
later what happened next: “Johann Frahm took a twelve-year-old boy in his arms and said to
the others: "Now I'm going to put him to bed." Then he took him to a room with a rope hanging
from a hook, about six or eight meters from where the other children were. He put the sleeping little one
on the rope and pulled the body down with all his strength, tightening the rope.”
After witnessing this horror, Trzebinski felt ill and left the building,
going around it several times. Shortly afterwards, he left Bullenhuser
Damm under the pretext of complying with other formalities. Meanwhile,
Frahm continued the crimes until all the Jewish children were hanged. His four
Caregivers, a doctor and three nurses, were also killed that night.
That same night, about 30 more Soviet prisoners were trucked to the school for
to be executed. They were guarded by Heinrich Wiehagen and Adolf Speck, the commander of the
Neuengamme brickyard, which shot one of the prisoners because he had thrown salt
in Speck's face. That night, six Soviet prisoners escaped, three were shot in the
attempt and the rest were hanged in the basement boiler room by Wilhelm Dreimann,
with the help of Heinrich Wiehagen and Johann Frahm, who later testified about it.
The next morning, Trzebinski returned to the school to officially confirm the death.
of all the victims. He also ordered all clothing, toys, and belongings to be burned.
of the children to destroy any evidence. Shortly after, Trzebinski returned to the camp
from Neuengamme and informed the commander, Max Pauly, that the children had been killed.
This crime became known as the Bullenhuser Damm Massacre.
After the capitulation of Germany in May 1945,
The murder of 20 children in the former school building on Bullenhuser Damm sparked outrage.
and public horror and the perpetrators were brought to justice.
After the war, SS doctor Kurt Heissmeyer, who had performed
the experiments on the murdered children, he escaped and returned to his home in Magdeburg,
in post-war East Germany, where he began a successful healthcare practice
as a specialist in lungs and tuberculosis. He was finally discovered in 1959 and arrested in
1963. In 1966, he was convicted and sentenced to life imprisonment. At his trial, he stated:
"I didn't believe that the inmates of a camp had full value as human beings."
However, the other perpetrators suffered a much worse fate.
On March 18, 1946, the trial of fourteen officials of the main
Neuengamme concentration camp before a British military tribunal,
in the Curiohaus building in Hamburg, Germany. It was the first of 33
trials that would be held over the next two years, driven by the British against
the staff of the Neuengamme concentration camp and its satellite camps.
Among the accused in these proceedings were also the perpetrators of the massacre of
Bullenhuser Damm, among whom was Alfred Trzebinski, who defended the murder
of 20 innocent children with the following words: "If I had acted like a hero,
The children might have died a little later, but their fate could no longer be avoided." He added:
"You can't execute children, you can only murder them, but they were 'only' Jews."
On May 3, 1946, eleven defendants, including Alfred Trzebinski,
the former commandant of Neuengamme Max Pauly, the camp executioner Wilhelm Dreimann and the
Commandant of the brick factory of the concentration camp Adolf Speck were
found guilty and sentenced to death by hanging. However, this was not the end.
In July 1946, Johann Frahm and Ewald Jauch were also sentenced to death,
executed by hanging on 8 and 11 October by British executioner Albert Pierrepoint.
Until their last breath, they remained staunch Nazis. The last words of Dr. Alfred
Trzebinski's words were as follows: "Father, forgive them, for they know not what they do."
Although they were almost lost at first after World War II,
The children's story and identity were finally discovered
Thanks to the investigation of German journalist Günther Schwarberg and his wife,
Lawyer Barbara Hüsing. Today, the children are remembered internationally.
Many tears were shed for all the victims of Nazi atrocities.
Thanks for watching World History Channel don't forget to like and subscribe
and click on the notification bell so you don't miss it
our next videos thanks See you next time on the channel and